29 Chapter 30 Of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su Chapter 30 A Thief My new master was an unmarried man.
He lived at B and was much engaged in business. His doctor advised him to take
horse exercise, and for this purpose he bought me. He hired a stable a short
distance from his lodgings, and engaged a man named Filcher as groom. My master
knew very little about horses, but he treated me well, and I should have had a
good and easy place but for circumstances of which he was ignorant.
He ordered the best hay with plenty of oats, crushed beans, and bran, with vetes
or Ry grass, as the man might think needful. I heard the master give the
order, so I knew there was plenty of good food, and I thought I was well
off. For a few days all went on well. I found that my groom understood his
business. He kept the stable clean and airy, and he groomed me thoroughly; and
was never otherwise than gentle. He had been a hustler in one of the great
hotels in Bath. He had given that up, and now cultivated fruit and vegetables for
the market, and his wife bread and fattened poultry and rabbits for
sale. After a while it seemed to me that my oats came very short; I had the beans,
but Brown was mixed with them instead of oats, of which there were very few;
certainly not more than a quarter of what there should have been. In two or 3
weeks this began to tell upon my strength and spirits. The grass food,
though very good, was not the thing to keep up my condition without corn.
However, I could not complain, nor make known my wants. So it went on for about two months;
and I wondered that my master did not see that something was the
matter. However, one afternoon he rode out into the country to see a friend of his,
a gentleman farmer, who lived on the road to Wells. This gentleman had a very quick
eye for horses; and after he had welcomed his friend he said, casting his eye over
me: “It seems to me, Barry, that your horse
does not look so well as he did when you first had him; has he been
well?” “Yes, I believe so,” said my master; “but
he is not nearly so lively as he was; my groom tells me that horses are always
dull and weak in the autumn, and that I must expect
it.” “Autumn, fiddlesticks!” said the farmer.
“Why, this is only August; and with your light work and good food he ought not to
go down like this, even if it was autumn.
How do you feed him?” My master told him.
The other shook his head slowly, and began to feel me
over. “I can't say who eats your corn, my dear fellow, but I am much mistaken if
your horse gets it. Have you ridden very fast?” “No, very gently.” “Then just put your
hand here,” said he, passing his hand over my neck and shoulder; “he is as warm and
damp as a horse just come up from grass.
I advise you to look into your stable a little more. I hate to be suspicious ious
and, thank heaven, I have no cause to be, for I can trust my men, present or absent;
but there are mean scoundrels, wicked enough to rob a dumb beast of his food.
You must look into it.” And turning to his man, who had come to take me, “Give this
horse a right good feed of bruised oats, and don't stint
him.” “Dumb beasts!” Yes, we are; but if I could have spoken I could have told my
master where his oats went to. My groom used to come every morning about 6:00
and with him a little boy, who always had a covered basket with him. He used to go
with his father into the harness room where the corn was kept, and I could see
them, when the door stood a jar fill a little bag with oats out of the bin, and
then he used to be off. Five or six mornings after this, just
as the boy had left the stable, the door was pushed open, and a policeman walked
in, holding the child tight by the arm; another policeman followed, and locked
the door on the inside, saying, “Show me the place where your father keeps his
rabbits' food.” The boy looked very frightened and began to cry; but there
was no escape, and he led the way to the corn bin Here the policeman found
another empty bag like that which was found full of oats in the boy's
basket fure was cleaning my feet at the time, but they soon saw him, and though he
blustered a good deal they walked him off to the lockup and his boy with him. I
heard afterward that the boy was not held to be guilty, but the man was
sentenced to prison for 2 months end of chapter